# Claudio Panariello

Curriculum Vitae

Sankt Paulsgatan 29D 118 48 Stockholm Sweden  $\$ +39 \ 3405365368$   $\bowtie cla.panariello@gmail.com$ 



## Personal Information

Name Claudio

Last name Panariello

Place and date of birth Napoli (NA), 07 October 1989

Citizenship Italian

# Biography

Born in Naples in 1989, he studied Composition and Piano. After a Bachelor's degree in Physics at University of Pisa with a thesis on Musical acoustics, he studies Electronic Music at Conservatory "S. Pietro a Majella" of Naples with A. Di Scipio and E. Martusciello (Bachelor's Degree) and then at Conservatory "S. Cecilia" of Rome with M. Lupone and N. Bernardini (Master's Degree).

He attended master classes and courses with a.o. F. Filidei, M. Lanza, R. Cendo, O. Bianchi, C. Czernowin, S. Steen-Andersen, Y. Maresz, S. Movio.

His music has been performed by Divertimento Ensemble, Ensemble SuonoGiallo, mdi ensemble, Neue Vocalsolisten Stuttgart, Ensemble Mise-En, Ensemble United Instruments of Lucilin, etc. and in festivals such as "Mise-En Music Festival" in New York, "Rondò" and "Sound of Wander" in Milano, "Festival delle Nazioni" in Citta di Castello, "Casa del Quartetto - Fondazione I Teatri" in Reggio Emilia, "Risuonanze" in Udine, etc.

He has also worked in sound installations field with "Fewy", exposed in the Sol LeWitt Hall of the Museo Madre (NA), "Studio in tre fasi", a site-specific sound installation at the Goethe Institut in Rome for ArteScienza Festival 2017, and "A mic in a box" for Ars Cyber != Dystopian at Incó ntemporanea Festival 2020.

In 2017 he wins the Divertimento Ensemble's "Concorso di Composizione AFAM" for young composers.

He is currently a PhD student in Sound and Music Computing at KTH Royal Institute of Technology in Stockholm, focusing on musical adaptive systems.

## **Education**

2018 - present PhD in Sound and Music Computing

at KTH Royal Institute of Technology, Stockholm.

2015 - 2017 Master's Degree in Electronic Music

with 110/110 cum laude at the Conservatory "Santa Cecilia" of Rome with Michelangelo Lupone and Nicola Bernardini.

2012 - 2015 Bachelor's Degree in Electronic Music

with  $110/110\ cum\ laude$  at the Conservatory "San Pietro a Majella" of Naples with Agostino Di Scipio and Elio Martusciello.

2013/2014 Bachelor's Degree in Physics

with 105/110 from University of Pisa with a thesis entitled "Physical characters of piano tones, their analysis and synthesis".

# 2008 Secondary school Diploma

from Liceo "Filippo Silvestri" of Portici (NA) with 100/100 cum laude.

# 2006 Student of Composition

at the conservatory "San Pietro a Majella" of Naples.

# Professional experience

2020 - 2021 **Teacher** at Sound in Interaction course (DT2300), KTH, from 18/01/2021 to present.

**Assistant** at Media Production course (DM1579/DM2579), KTH, from Oct/2020 to Jan/2021.

**Teacher** at Program Development for Interactive Media (SuperCollider course) (DM1595), KTH, from Sept/2020 to Oct/2020.

**Assistant** at Multimodal Interaction and Interfaces course (DT2140), KTH, Nov/2020.

**Teacher** at Introduction to Media Technology course (DM1581), KTH, Sept/2020.

2019 - 2020 **Teacher** at Sound in Interaction course (DT2300), KTH, from 15/01/2020 to present.

**Assistant** at Human-Computer Interaction, Introductory Course (DH1620), KTH, Sept/Oct 2019.

**Assistant** at Multimodal Interaction and Interfaces course (DT2140), KTH, from 12/11/2019 to 15/01/2019.

**Teacher** at Introduction to Media Technology course (DM1581), KTH, from Oct/2019 to Jan/2020.

**Assistant** at Media Production course (DM1579/DM2579), KTH, from Oct/2019 to Jan/2020.

2018 - 2019 **Teacher** at Sound in Interaction course (DT2300), KTH, from 15/01/2019 to 15/03/2019.

**Assistant** at Human-Computer Interaction, Introductory Course (DH1620), KTH, from 15/01/2019 to 23/05/2019.

**Assistant** at Multimodal Interaction and Interfaces course (DT2140), KTH, from 01/11/2018 to 13/01/2018.

**Teacher** at Introduction to Media Technology course (DM1581), KTH, from 03/09/2018 to 25/10/2018.

2017 - 2018 **Professor** of Musical Technologies at Liceo Musicale e Coreutico "Aladino Di Martino" in Portici (NA).

## Courses and Masterclasses

## 2019 ManiFeste 2019 - Academy

workshop of Composition for chamber music and electronics with ensemble Nikel, Raphaël Cendo and IRCAM computer-music designers Grégoire Lorieux and Mikhail Malt.

# NordicSMC Winter School

Intensive PhD-level training course on sound and motion analysis with experts in sound and music computing from the Nordic countries.

#### 2018 Ticino Musica 2018

Workshop of Composition with Oscar Bianchi, Bernhard Gander and Neue Vocalsolisten Stuttgart.

# International Workshop for Young Composers 2018

Workshop of Composition with Francesco Filidei and Mauro Lanza.

#### Masterclass with Simon Steen-Andersen

Sound of Wander, Milano.

# 2017 Luxembourg Composition Academy 2017

Workshop of Composition with Chaya Czernowin and Mauro Lanza.

# Masterclass with Chaya Czernowin

Sound of Wander, Milano.

## Livorno Music Festival 2017

Masterclass with Yan Maresz.

# "2nd International ilSuono Academy for Young Composers"

Workshop of Composition with Simone Movio e Nicolas Tzortzis.

#### Masterclass with Francesco Filidei

Accademia Musicale Toscana, Pontedera.

# "International Composition Course Institut Franais - Barcelona Modern Project"

Workshop of Composition with Raphael Cendo.

## 2016 Masterclass with Luis Naon

Conservatory "Santa Cecilia", Rome.

#### Masterclass with John Chowning

Conservatory "Santa Cecilia", Rome.

## Livorno Music Festival 2016

Masterclass with Christopher Austin.

## International Workshop for Young Composers 2016

Workshop of Composition with Alessandro Solbiati and Mauro Lanza.

#### Masterclass with Curtis Roads

Conservatory "Santa Cecilia", Rome.

#### Masterclass with Johan Van Kreij

Conservatory "G. Martucci", Salerno.

#### 2015 Masterclass with Ivan Fedele

Nuova Consonanza, Rome.

# 2013 Intensive program "ART of SOUND - SOUND of ART"

Conservatory "S. Giacomantonio", Cosenza.

# Honors

#### 2020 ManiFeste 2020

Selected for writing a new piece for Ensemble Nikel and Electronics at IRCAM, scheduled for ManiFeste 2020. **CANCELLED due to COVID-19 pandemic.** 

## 2017 Sound of Wander 2017

Macchina Anatomica selected for SOW 2017 by mdi ensemble.

## ilSUONO Contemporary Music Week

Piccolo inventario degli insetti selected for including in repertoire of Ensemble Suono Giallo + honorable mention.

#### Concorso AFAM

Winner Concorso AFAM 2017 and commission of a new piece for Divertimento Ensemble "Rondò 2018" season.

# MISE-EN Festival 2017

Flebili stelle nere selected for MISE-EN Festival 2017.

#### 2016 Peter Maxwell Davies Prize

Commission of a new piece for Contemporatensemble.

#### 2016 Risuonanze **2016**

Filla-ma-loo-bird selected for "Risuonanze - Incontri di nuove musiche 2016".

#### 2014 Absolute I Prize

at the "II Concorso di Composizione in Clausura" of the 100 Cellos Ensemble of Giovanni Sollima: the piece has been published by Casa Editrice Sonzogno.

#### III Prize

at the "III International Composing Competition Antonio Smareglia" with "Miraggi" for piano.

#### 2013 Teatro Valle

Selected by Teatro Valle Occupato (Roma) as one of the five composers to write the music for their first theatrical production, the "Slaughter of Job", directed by Fausto Paravidino. The show debuted in world premiere at the Bozar Theatre in Brussels on 15 and 16 October 2014.

#### II Prize

at the "Wanda Landowska Harpsichord Competition" with Toccatina for harpsichord.

# List of works and Performances

## 2021 New work

for String Quartet and electronics, commissioned by Maurice Quartet.

# Ongoing artistic research project

in collaboration with Chiara Percivati.

#### 2020 Private journal of dreams

for Ensemble and electronics, commissioned by Collettivo\_21, 10'.

• 9/10/2020, Incó\_ntemporanea Festival 2020. Volumnia, Ex Chiesa di S. Agostino, Piacenza, Italy.

## Discover of Television among the bees

for Ensemble and Electronics, written for Ensemble Nikel and for ManiFeste 2020.

• CANCELLED due to COVID-19 emergency.

# Mini self-portrait with Nancarrow and Mažulis (with Ligeti in the title)

for Electric Guitar, Accordion and Theorbo, 42", written for Azione\_Improvvisa Ensemble, not intended to be performed live.

• https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Pa\_EwecwjH8

## Rage over hearing loss

for String Trio and Orchestra, 10', commissioned by Ensemble Broken Frames Syndicate and Lüneburger Symphoniker.

• 25/10/12 Theater, Lüneburg, Lüneburg, Germany.

# 2019 Clever Hans is introduced to Dr. Oskar Pfungst

for four String Quartets distributed in the space, 22'.

• 16/06/2019, Quartetto A&C, Quartetto Al Pari, Quartetto Cesar Franck, Quartetto Reflex. Casa del Quartetto, Chiostri di San Pietro, Reggio Emilia (Italy).

## Study for Dissipatio H.G.

for String Stextet, 7'.

- 29/11/2019, ContempoartEnsemble, Palazzo Medici Riccardi, Firenze (Italy).
- 01/12/2019, ContemportEnsemble, Prato (Italy).

# Automaton for Liquefying Blood

for Violin and fixed media, 8'.

- 17/09/2019, Lorenzo Derinni vn, Davide Gagliardi el., Wien.
- 19/09/2019, Lorenzo Derinni vn, Davide Gagliardi el., Klagenfurt.

## 2018 1968 - Praga Primavera

Theatre production on text by Ivan Teobaldelli, for Ensemble and electronics., 55'.

- 03/09/2018 Ensemble Suono Giallo, M. Perugini voice, Festival delle Nazioni 2018. Teatro degli Illuminati, Città di Castello (PG), Italy.
- 25/05/2019 Ensemble Suono Giallo, M. Perugini voice, Sala della Pace (G.C.), Cascia (Italy).

#### Three Haiku

for 4 male voices, 8'.

• 29/07/2018 Neue Vocalsolisten Stuttgart, Ticino Musica, LAC, Lugano, Switzerland.

# Autopsia su una marionetta

for Ensemble, 7'30".

• 14/07/2018 Divertimento Ensemble, Sandro Gorli cond., IWFYC 2018, Bobbio (PC), Italy.

#### Mitologia del Principe

for oboe, bass clarinet, piano and 3 percussionists, 12'.

• 19/03/2018 Divertimento Ensemble, Sandro Gorli cond., Rondò 2018, Palazzina Liberty, Milano, Italy.

- 2017 The ships hung in the sky in much the same way that bricks don't for piano, e-guitar and electronics, 4'15".
  - 13/12/2017 Duo Santorsa Saccone, Theater Pavillon, Luzern (CH).
  - 15/12/2017 Duo Santorsa Saccone, Druckereihalle im Ackermannshof, Basel (CH).
  - 16/12/2017 Duo Santorsa Saccone, Literaturcaf Biel, Biel (CH).
  - 29/12/2017 Duo Santorsa Saccone, Dialoghi sul comporre Torri dell'acqua, Budrio (BO), Italy.

#### universi-isole

for Wind Quintet, 7'.

• 03/09/2017 Ensemble in residence, Livorno Music Festival 2017, Fortezza Vecchia, Livorno, Italy.

## Piccolo inventario degli insetti

for bass flute, sax, percussion, piano and electronics, 7'.

- 22/07/2017 Ensemble Suono Giallo, "2nd International ilSuono Academy for Young Composers", Sala degli Specchi del Circolo degli Illuminati, Città di Castello (PG), Italy.
- 18/11/2017 United Instruments of Lucilin, Garrett Keast cond., "Luxembourg Composition Academy", Neimënster, salle Robert Krieps, Luxembourg City, Luxembourg.
- 14/07/2019 Ensemble Suono Giallo, Teatro Comunale, Città di Castello (PG), Italy.

# Bottiglie di Klein

for two flutes, 6'10".

• 18/06/2017 Fosca Briante, Tiziano Cantoni, flutes. Risuonanze 2017, Pasian di Prato (UD), Italy.

# Passaggio (new vers.)

for bass clarinet and cello, 4'20".

- 9/06/2017 Ensemble Via Nova, 68. Atelierkonzert Begegnung der Künste, Jena, Germany.
- 19/07/2017 Ensemble Via Nova, Sala degli Specchi del Circolo degli Illuminati, Città di Castello (PG), Italy.
- 28/10/2017 Ensemble Via Nova, Kunsthaus sans titre, Potsdam, Germany.
- 26/10/2018 Ensemble Via Nova, Erfurt, Germany.
- $\bullet$  14/12/2018 Kaorou Nishimura and Kei Yamazawa, Salon Tessera, Tokyo, Japan.
- 08/10/2019 Ensemble Via Nova, Berlin, Germany.

## Theatrum Insectorum

for bass clarinet, piano and electronics, 7'.

- 12/05/2017 Morphosis Ensemble. Barcelona Modern Project International Workshop for Young Composers, Barcelona, Spain.
- 25/10/2017 Cum Tempora Ensemble. EMUFest X, Conservatorio Santa Cecilia, Roma, Italy.

## 2016 Flebili Stelle Nere

for flute, clarinet, percussion, violin and cello, 8'.

- 7/09/2016 Ensemble in residence, Livorno Music Festival 2016, Museo Civico Giovanni Fattori, Livorno, Italy.
- 3/04/2017 Divertimento Ensemble, Sandro Gorli cond. Rondò 2017. Piccolo Teatro Studio Melato, Milano, Italy.
- 24/06/2017 Ensemble Mise-en, Moon Young HA cond. Mise-En Music Festival 2017. Taipei Cultural Center, New York, USA.

#### Macchina Anatomica

for flute, bass clarinet, percussion, piano, violin and cello, 6'30".

- 16/07/2016 Divertimento Ensemble, Sandro Gorli cond., IWFYC 2016, Bobbio (PC), Italy.
- 20/12/2017 mdi ensemble, Armando Merino cond., SOW#4, Auditorium Lattuada, Milano, Italy.

## Fearsom critters no.1: Filla-Ma-Loo-Bird

for piano solo, 3'.

• 30/05/2016 Adele D'Aronzo, pno. Risuonanze 2016, Tarcento (UD), Italy.

## Elogio dell'ombra

for solo violin, 6'50'.

- 18/03/2016 Vittorio Fusco, vno. Contemporanea... mente. Chiesa del Carmine, Avellino, Italy.
- 19/03/2016 Vittorio Fusco, vno. Festival 5 Giornate. Mudec, Milano, Italy.

## Rhapsody on a windy night

for clarinet, bass clarinet and piano, 7'15".

- 6/03/2016 Trio Najma. Arianna Tieghi, cl.; Luca Lenzi, bass cl.; Ilenia La Rocca, pno. Salotto Culturale Aggazzotti, Modena, Italy.
- 2/08/2016 Trio Najma. Estate musicale del Conservatorio. Auditorium "Claudio Monteverdi", Mantova, Italy.
- 14/05/2017 Trio Najma. Stagione Classicalessandria 2017. Teatro Comunale Sala Ferrero, Alessandria, Italy.
- 15/09/2017 Trio Najma. ClariÉNote di fine estate. Tresigallo (FE), Italy.
- 30/11/2019 Trio Najma. Cerveteri, Italy.

## 2015 Esercitar mi sole

audiovisual work, 15'.

- 30/12/2015 Electronics Lab. Palazzo Fazio, Capua (CE), Italy.
- 13/02/2016 Chiesa di San Rocco a Chiaia, Napoli. Italy.

# Passaggio

for trombone and viola, 3'50".

• 15/11/2015 Michele Lomuto, trombone, Cristiano Rossi, viola. Autunno Musicale, Duomo di Casertavecchia (CE), Italy.

## Electroacoustic performance

26/10/2015 in Duo at "PAN - Palazzo delle Arti Napoli" (NA) and performance of "Dies J." (electroacoustic composition), Italy.

#### Jommelli Remix

8/06/2015 with Ensemble Officina Arti Soniche at the conservatory of Naples "San Pietro a Majella" and performance of "Dies J." (electroacoustic composition), Italy.

## 2014 Electroacoustic performance

28/10/2014 in Duo at ElectronicaFest, Mostra d'Oltremare (NA), Italy.

## Electroacoustic performance

6/10/2014 with Ensemble Officina Arti Soniche at the Galleria Toledo (NA), Italy.

#### Electroacoustic performance

01/10/2014 with Ensemble Officina Arti Soniche at OLE.01 Festival, Conservatory of Naples "San Pietro a Majella", Napoli, Italy.

# Energico

for Cello Ensemble (4 parts), 2'30".

- 25/05/2014 Ensemble 100Cellos, Giovanni Sollima cond., Teatro dell'Arte, Milano, Italy.
- 3-4-5/07/2014 Ensemble 100Cellos. Inauguration Concert for the Italian Presidency of the European Union, Budapest, Hungary.

#### Toccatina

for harpsichord, 3'20".

• 05/04/2014 Annalisa Ficarra, hpd. Festival Wanda Landowska, Ruvo di Puglia (BA), Italy.

## 2013 Rapsodia Urbana

for 2 pianos 24 hands, 7'45".

- 19/12/2013 Auditorium Istituto Comprensivo "Antonio Custra", Cercola (NA), Italy.
- $\bullet$  18/05/2014 Stravaganze Musicali. Sala delle Arti, Manocalzati (AV), Italy.
- 01/07/2014 Non solo due... mani. Conservatory of Naples "San Pietro a Majella", Napoli, Italy.
- 31/05/2016 Circolo della Marina Militare, Napoli, Italy.
- $\bullet$ 04/06/2016 Fonderia Righetti, Villa Bruno, San Giorgio a Cremano (NA), Italy.
- 06/06/2016 Castello Santa Caterina, Pollena Trocchia (NA), Italy.
- 20/01/2018 Auditorium Conservatorio "Domenico Cimarosa", Avellino, Italy.
- $\bullet$  29/03/2019 Sala Scarlatti, Conservatory of Naples "San Pietro a Majella", Napoli, Italy.

## Der Mond

for clarinet and piano, 8'.

- 21/09/2013 Guido Arbonelli, cl., Antonella Giovannelli, pno. Clarinet Trend Day, II Ed., Avellino, Italy.
- 20/02/2015 Duo Catensemble. Natalia Benedetti, cl., Michela Caldesi, pno. Armonie di intesa, Biblioteca San Matteo degli Armeni, Perugia, Italy.

#### 2007 **Duo**

for violin and piano, 7'.

• 11/05/2007. Francesco Solombrino, vno., Ciro Longobardi, pno (members of Ensemble Dissonanzen). Conservatory of Naples "San Pietro a Majella", Napoli, Italy.

#### 2006 La casa di Asterione

for flute, piano, violin, cello, 7'30".

• 7/04/2006 Ensemble Dissonanzen, Conservatory of Naples "San Pietro a Majella", Napoli, Italy.

Sound installations

#### 2020 A mic in a box

A real physical space, the wine cellar of Villa Ghizzoni Nasalli in Piacenza (Italy). A specific space closed to the public and inaccessible except than virtually. The audience is invited to virtually join the room through a specifically designed website, pressing the record button and sending through your device's microphone 30 seconds (maximum) of audio into the cellar: you can speak, sing, play an instrument, scream or even remain silent, thus sending the background sound of the environment you are inhabiting now. All the traces of virtual passages will be played in the cellar and will interact live with all the elements present in there and with its acoustic footprint, as well as with all the traces of the other virtual visitors. A camera pointed at that real yet segregated space makes everything that happens in there accessible outside.

A mic in a box was part of the project Ars Cyber != Dystopian with Luca Guidarini and Alessandro Perini and presented at Incó\_ntemporanea Festival 2020.

• 11/10/2020 00.00 am – 11.59 pm Incó\_ntemporanea Festival 2020, Palazzo Ghizzoni Nasalli, Piacenza, (Italy).

# 2017 Studio in tre fasi

22 solenoids, 2 microcontrollers, cables, laptop.

This is a site-specific interactive sound installation inspired by the architecture of the porch inside the garden of the Goethe Institut in Rome. The aim of the work is to make this space musical creating a sort of sound path that is sensitive to the spectator's presence with which it tries to dialogue and at the same time suggesting a new acoustic interpretation of the chosen space.

- 17-22/07/2017 "Il Giardino dei Suoni Segreti", ArteScienza 2017, Goethe Institut, Roma, (Italy).
- 28/12/2019 Festival "Stanze di Musica", Casa della Cultura e delle Arti, Camerota (Salerno, Italy).

## 2014 Fewy - Few Events With Ynteractions

2 mics, 2 speakers, laptop.

The aim is to communicate acoustically with the room using the reflections on the walls of a sound material designed specifically for that space and reprocessing each time the results obtained.

• 13/11/2014 Sala Sol LeWitt, Museo Madre, Napoli, Italy.

# **Publications**

Panariello, C. (2020). Study in three phases: An Adaptive Sound Installation. Leonardo Music Journal, 30, 44-49.

Latupeirissa, A., Panariello C., and Bresin R. Exploring emotion perception in sonic HRI. Sound and Music Computing Conference, Torino, 24-26 June 2020. Zenodo, 2020.

Panariello C. et al., From vocal sketching to sound models by means of a sound-based musical transcription system, in Proceedings of the 16th Sound and Music Computing Conference, 2019, s. 1-7.

Piccolo Inventario degli Insetti, on d.a.t. [divulgazioneaudiotestuale], n.1. 2017, edizioni EdiPsy, ISBN 978-88-941104-8-7.

- "Le berceuse di Aldo Clementi: I e II", on "Civiltà musicale n.70", LoGisma editore, ISBN 978-88-97530-78-7.
- "Energico", Casa Musicale Sonzogno.
- "Der Mond", edizioni Forton Music.
- "Rapsodia Urbana", edizioni Il Monocordo Montecorvino Rovella (SA), ISBN 979-0-9001046-4-9.
- "Correnti Telluriche", edizioni Il Monocordo Montecorvino Rovella (SA), ISMN 979-0-9001046-6-3.